hello and welcome it's March 14 2023 and
we're in active bookstream
1.010 off to you blue
um today we are going to be discussing
this governing and continuing
transformation book we're moving into
the third and final section of the text
um and so we're going to kick it off
today and next week and we will wrap up
our discussion of the book over these
next couple of weeks so we are the
active inference Institute
a participatory online Institute that is
communicating learning and practicing
applied active inference these are all
of our social media links this live
stream is recorded and archived so
please provide us with feedback so that
we can improve on our work all
backgrounds and perspectives are welcome
and we will be following good video
etiquette for live streams
um if you would like to get involved in
this project or any of the ongoing
projects at The Institute
um get in touch reach out at
activeinference.org I think we're
actually activeinference.institute now
too so either one works
um okay so we are in the 10th chapter
of this governing continuous
transformation book we're going to
actually discuss chapters 10 and 11
today this final section really is just
a um
a conclusion and wrap-up of the
information that's been presented in
sections one and two so we can just
introduce ourselves briefly I am blue
Knight an independent researcher in New
Mexico and I will pass it off
I'm Tyler I'm a dow researcher and
particle designer in California Daniel
I'm Daniel I'm a researcher in
California
oh okay
so doing this
third part the conclusion part the
chapters today so chapter 10 is really
just an abstract which we'll read and
then it's like a giant table summarizing
um the free energy governance model
versus traditional corporate governance
and so we'll just cover that and just
summarize how how these are the same and
different and then we'll get into
chapter 11 and some of the content the
conclusion content that is presented
there
um Tyler do you want to read this one
for us and we'll take the next part
sure so through the lens of the
theoretical Concepts developed in this
book FEG and traditional corporate
governance kcg are assassin comparative
uh perspective TCG models are
predominantly characterized by a
compliance mentality centered around
where the effectiveness as a matter of
managing agency conflicts of interest
through optimizing stereotypical core
diversity enforcing director
Independence
fpg introduces a radically new logic
exercising the corporate wholesale
reinvention as strategic renewal was
down posing indeed any such disposition
of two Governors Logics can hardly
escape the accusation of
oversimplification however once we
embrace the world as discontinuous and
distributed you start understanding that
today's trans corporate governance
approaches are low-scale low leverage
Legacy business for the international
well and I'll just read the second part
public policy prescribes best practices
guiding corporate governance is an
anachronism of modern business
reinforcing upper echelon's risk
aversiveness I.E compromising epistemic
foraging and consequently entrapment in
the incapacitating perception of the
world as volatile and certain complex
and ambiguous or vuca
free energy governance Embraces any
dimension of vuca as information Rich
input for top-down bottom-up prediction
error minimization in pursuit of
minimizing surprise
an over-reliance on CEO framed
information flows and Analysis which is
so characteristic of traditional
corporate governance is as good as
flipping a coin the very processes that
explain success equally breed failure
um and this table 10.1 there's a little
bit in the chapter but this table 10.1
is um like one of the very few figures
or tables presented in the entire text
if not the only one
um and here we can just see like there's
three columns the first is the logic
um and then the second is free energy
governance like how it um relates to
that logic and then the third column is
traditional corporate governance and how
how that relates to the logic so um for
example so here the structure or
hierarchy is the logic
um where the free energy governance
method is top down bottom up um top-down
belief propagation and bottom up message
passing
in circular causality unidirectional
upper echelon belief propagation only so
there's not that bi-directional
information flow and the process uh for
free energy governance is generative or
continuous and traditional corporate
governance
is static or agenda
capabilities are meta Dynamic uh
cognitive in free energy governance and
operational or domain-centric in
traditional corporate governance
um the dominant neural network is this
um direct oh no default default mode
Network direct default I think it's
default default mode Centric Network
um and then the traditional corporate
governance is Task positive Network
Centric so this is interesting to me
like I thought that um
when we were talking about these neural
networks it was really like the um
conjunction of the two networks that I
thought was characteristic of free
energy governance as opposed to like one
neural network being more dominant than
another uh did you guys get that too or
or is this like
I don't know to me like I think that
this is kind of like weird this took me
by surprise
I think when they say like DMS Centric
we're not saying that one is limited to
free governance or TCG they're just
saying that there's more of an emphasis
on this kind of exploratory default mode
processing with free energy governance
but you still like have to do you know
switch between explore and exploit or
actually uh switch between but pursue
them both simultaneously and so those
are happening in parallel is my
understanding at least
yeah agreed with that Tyler and also
is it the case that the normal operating
function is Task oriented and then we
pull back to review
or is it the case that we're pulled back
in review and then we drop into the task
that's like DN dmn Centric but in both
cases you still would want the effective
oscillation
um and then the learning for free energy
governance is double Loop learning and
single single Loop prevails in the
traditional corporate governance
and then there's different performance
performance metrics and performance
variables and
corporate purpose which um I I don't
know that we like got too into that
text like this is kind of maybe
um it was like lacking so I was
surprised to see this here the corporate
purpose so he says in free energy
governance it's existential and
axiomatically integral to the free
energy minimizing governance mandate
like the purpose is that
um where in traditional corporate
governance it's diffused and
opportunistic with no relevance to
governance
um so maybe I like just skimmed over
that or like blanked it uh from the text
but this is from like the very the very
first chapter so this is like you know
what 13 live streams again that uh
they're just linking like
corporations want to survive linking
that very much into like calling out the
corporate purposes to to survive to you
on
cool so then um the second part of this
table uh we talked about
um strategic and financial control like
the Dual mandate Management in FEG where
traditional corporate governance is
focused on financial
environmental engagement we talked about
infrared energy governance as an
enactment
um with traditional corporate governance
is adaptation
um digital transformation uh which is
like that's interesting
um like it's an interesting logic like
the logic of digital transformation
um where FEG is holistic wholesale
reinvention and traditional corporate
governance is selective
transformation or domain specific
um but like I I'm like having a hard
time relating to this digital
transformation logic
[Music]
I think what he potentially might mean
to like say that you're a business that
like sells something and like so you
sell it over the counter right The
Selective transformation would be like
okay well now we have like a web check
out flow but the digital like these
wholesale reinvention could be like
you know using AI to take your Bottoms
Up input to transform those into
top-down predictions right like really
doing something fundamentally different
with
um your digital tools rather than just
like mapping physical processes into
digital as my understanding
um and then strategic renewal uh is
autonomous under free energy governance
proactive um and it's like this dual
information flow again where in
traditional corporate governance it's
induced or reactive top-down mandates
driven by belief propagation
uh the machine learning logic
um
I thought this was cool and maybe I
don't know Ruby Daniel wants to speak
more to this
um as we've been talking about the need
for free energy minimization in active
inference or not so the machine learning
logic in free energy governance is
optimizing the principle of least action
to resist dissipation in order to
persist
um in traditional corporate governance
it's like supervised or rule-based
maximizing predetermined reward
functions
um I don't know Daniel do you want to
speak any more to that uh just as you I
know you've been like thinking about it
okay the first thought was free energy
balance surprisal we would minimize our
surprisal if we had the perfect
generative model so minimizing surprisal
is like having the most model evidence
and we're going to bounce appraisal with
free energy minimization
and so in this machine learning logic
it's almost like we're going to bound
our surprisal
so that we can persist and thrive in our
niche
on the other side it's almost like we're
going to be following best practices and
compliance getting to the governance
mandate below we're going to be bounding
and staying within lines on all of the
checklists and then question mark
question mark question mark
we will have impact in the niche
whereas in free energy governance
surprisal minimization slash bounding
as a first imperative
ends up taking on some of those
outcomes that
under the traditional corporate
governance column would be seen as
consequences of of reducing mismatch
with compliance and regulation
cool thank you
um and then finally the final
um item in the table the logic is the
governance mandate under the free energy
governance is continuous strategic
renewal firm out performance and firm
survival
um
so like optimizing governance and
operational coupling environmental
enactment and dynamic Duality management
of exploration exploitation as well as
financial and strategic control
um all powered by inactive inference
um and then traditional corporate
governance is Regulatory Compliance
board Effectiveness from performance
um by monitoring advising challenging
boundary spanning networking all Guided
by CEO Centric and principally up for
Echelon dominated frames
um and so this like table in a nutshell
like really sums up a lot of the
concepts that we've discussed throughout
the text and what we are kind of looking
for in this new governance model
uh
maybe Tyler do you want to read the
first half of this abstract for chapter
11.
so how can one possibly redefine the
more strategic role when traditional
governance Motors deeper the sweet
entrenched and cognitive capabilities so
poorly developed or non-manifest
to be practiced around and Theory must
be intuitive and Inspire upper echelon
questioning it's very hardness of mind
to concede strategic renewal is
continuous and during the process of
top-down predictions bottom of stimuli
surprise immunization urges upper
echelon to consequently optimize the
multi-intelligence sources of stimuli
redesign processes as well as incentive
structures and develop a new language to
empower and active inference indeed to
date corporate governance research and
practice are more concerned with
defining behavioral responsibilities
rather than addressing its very
capability needs
thanks I'll take the second part
there is no
one-size-fits-all best practices catalog
but feg's Nexus of structure cognition
and capabilities provides the building
blocks for a fundamentally new
governance logic in a discontinuous
world the essential governance challenge
is to ensure the self-organizing
optimization of top down bottom-up
prediction error minimization learning
to infer once we embrace the fpg as a
novel organizational framework and early
detector of firms impending entropic
Decay we must reckon that unless
replaced with an fpg inspired logic
traditional corporate governance is
likely to continue relegating the board
of directors to strategic irrelevance
reinforce Financial control at the
expense of strategic control prioritize
top-down content over top-down bottom-up
processes cultivate inertia and inhibit
the full growth and survival potential
of firms as self-organizing systems
um and so this chapter had some sections
in it that I just tried to summarize
um here and so he talks about
um
the dimensions of the theory and like
the relevance he says the relevance of
theory to the practice of strategy
management and governance is essentially
determined by three dimensions Theory
must first be intuitive as well as a
problem or opportunity driven
second establish new metaphors or give
new meaning to existing language that
empowers purposeful sensing sense making
and strategic renewable and third
Inspire upper echelon questioning its
very habits of mind I.E provide a new
and enriching perspective around doing
things differently
um and this like I what I brought up the
theory particularly because like what's
not here in the dimension of like a
theory or like the relevance of theory
to the practice of strategy management
and like I don't have any background in
this so maybe Tyler you want to say some
more about it but like I feel like the
relevance of theory to the practice of
strategy management like for me what's
missing through this text and like we
get like I think we're getting a little
bit more into it now and we've uncovered
it but it's like not very obvious it's
like how do you find a practice that's
grounded in this Theory like what are
specific practices that this theory is
imploring us as a firm to do so I don't
know Tyler do you want to speak maybe to
that and just in terms of strategy
management overall like do all theories
do that or am I just like where is the
hard evidence maybe I'm just being a
stickler well first stop looking good
grounding and like economics and
corporate theory is that most of it is
wrong and I completely like a
lot of like even like microeconomics
theory is like totally debunked never
was correct in the first place and so
there's a very low bar for like having a
good theory like economics or corporate
governance oh with that said like I'm
trying to think of what makes pre-energy
governance like different to process
than like other kind of business
managers in the past
and like usually with other business
management theories like there's do
these 15 Steps right here is your best
practice guide to what this looks like
whereas with free energy governance it's
like not at all because it has to be
receptive to your environment so it
really demands like a spiritual uh
imbalance of these principles to like
really do or even understand about like
it really is like a spiritual I I keep
coming back like that's what it feels
like and you have to like really own
this and internalize it for it to be
used whereas like you don't have to
understand you don't have to feel that
with anything else in economics or
corporate governance you can just like
follow the steps but here like
a lot of the same things we talk about
corporate you know free energy
governance are the same ways we talk
about like creativity for example and a
lot about spiritual practices it's like
a very like receptive Dynamic
environmental practice which like you
really can't just put down to a series
of concrete steps uh and so that's why I
feel like I think this is spoke so
powerful and also so frustrating at the
same time because it's just like it's
like how do you be creative or like I
don't know like this is something you
figure out by in conversation with your
environment right it's the same thing
with free energy governance like the
most powerful things you can get from
this Theory No One's Gonna like be able
to directly teach you you have to kind
of just live it
um so yeah so calling is a theory is
like even though it is grounded in like
hardcore maths
at least for like the way a lot of like
business people including myself will
practice it does not feel that way at
all it feels much more of like a
spiritual like mindset
and that's very new for like a lot of
these kind of I've hadn't experienced
that before in a business context
I'll I'll give a few other notes thank
you Tyler very interesting
um the first point that theory should be
problem or opportunity oriented I think
blue that's where we would feel like we
were getting our hands dirty with the
theory and free energy governance gives
a continuity between what might be
happening in the analytics Department
with the actual generative models and in
the communications department and the
tools they use and in the boardroom
whereas one thing that we could say
about the traditional corporate
governance theories is
whether they were more mindset based or
more behavioral and practice based
their
limitation in relevance
was that they were doing these three
points but then what would the work
actually be about
what would the machine learning engineer
actually be doing something totally ad
hoc so there was always this like
disarticulation between the narratives
and the values and the broader purpose
of the organization and then the
implementation so
here we're coming from the upper echelon
to the front line and part of FEG is I
think that by being imbued in theory
even if this book was not heavily
equation or simulation based yet
it can provide a
continuity within the organism within
the corporation
so I like hear that um that you brought
in spirituality Tyler and I'm sorry like
it says my internet connection is
unstable so I'll apologize in advance if
I'm cutting in and out
um but I like how you brought in
spirituality to this and also creativity
um because here it's like the the job of
the theory is to inspire upper echelon
like questioning
their own habits right and so like in
this way it's very like it's like a koan
right like like it's like you know some
puzzle that you sit down to just like
think about and solve and reflect upon
so like the job of the theory is to be
like a like a spiritual Quran like to
just think about it
um and then secondly like the creativity
part
um you're talking about creativity Tyler
and also like um interaction with the
environment like the the what it's
brought about literally by like
interacting with the environment and
there's a really cool book um that I
don't know if either of you guys have
read or heard about it's called the
artist's way and like literally it's
just like a series of tasks that like
get you into your environment so that
you're like inspired to be more creative
it's like a series of just like um it's
it's in its own way like its own Riddler
puzzle to be reflected on
um in that that's what they lead you
through in that book so it's just and
it's actually it's actually why I
mentioned that because I'm
simultaneously reading the artist's way
and also uh Rick Rubin it's like famous
producer he just uh released a book
about creativity and like the way that
they were talking about
um creativity in both these books is
very much about like Bottoms Up sense
making and like listening to your
environment I was like wow like a lot of
even like the language is the same with
governance because like at some level
we're talking about like the same thing
um and so it's just like again that's
what movies I love about creation
governance is that it is so Broad and
can Encompass all these different
disciplines from creativity corporate
governance you know and colonies
whatever
just a few short notes uh receptivity is
not passivity it's the opposite it's the
sentient engagements and the receptivity
with the generative process
that fine-tunes our generative model so
that we can be who we expect and prefer
to be so receptive and engaged with the
niche does not mean sitting back that's
probably been clear and then also
the framework
shouldn't be providing specifics I know
that's a normative claim but it's like
if somebody said I have a linear
regression machine and it always comes
up with positive linear regressions and
be like well let's maybe separate that
let's have the neutral linear regressor
and then we can have a second order
preference for ones that are positive or
let's filter out the ones that are
positive only
so in a way because it is a framework or
a theory for this strategic renewal
discussion which is the positioning of
the book
it is at a level above any specific
practice because just like you couldn't
say well a wing or a tooth or a poison
is like simply a high Fitness
adaptation of an organism outside of its
context and Niche there's no practice or
any pattern that would apply to all
different organisms or organizations in
their Niche so the discussion had to be
moved back to this not ultimately
neutral space in fact the very
principled space but one that gave the
expressivity to then specialize
according to the dimensions that we
basically looked at in the parts of the
book and in this table from today
awesome thanks
okay so moving on from the dimensions of
theory I think Bijan goes through like a
very uh good summary of like all of the
all all the things up until this point I
think
um so he says free energy governance
provides rich and new meaning to
existing Concepts and establishes new
relationships first top down bottom-up
prediction processing is applied to
strategic management and defined in form
of a generative process integrating
circular causality in circular causality
top-down belief propagation and
bottom-up message passing in pursuit of
one objective minimize surprise to
resist entropy to persist powered by one
first order principle of least action
I.E free energy minimization a
purpose-directed firm is the foundation
for free energy governance's top-down
bottom-up circular causality to come and
stay alive and he goes on to say in the
same context that upper echelon
communication is centered around four
dimensions dynamically Linked In feg's
circular causality purpose prediction
models predictions and stimuli the
Simplicity and plasticity of the
language are critical to ensure that
reach and inclusion of team members are
optimized
more importantly firm members must be
incentivized to stimuli challenge
predictions
um
underlying prediction models according
to the first order free energization
principle will self-evidently evolve by
the way of unsupervised
self-organization and he refers back to
like the structure of cognition and
capabilities that we've been linking
through this entire text uh so this I um
I I like and I but I I'm not um
I'm not sure how to like he says the
Simplicity and plasticity of the
language are critical to ensure that
reach and inclusion of team members are
optimized
I'm not sure how to do that but it's
like
um how do you make language simple and
plastic to you know ensure optimal reach
and inclusion inclusivity
um I don't know if you guys have
thoughts on that like I'm like where are
my step-by-step procedures that I'm
supposed to follow to make this happen
I think there's many angles on it just a
few comments one a starting point would
be making sure that the language are in
the native or preferred tongue of that
person or augmented entity so having the
active inference ontology translated
into multiple language is one first step
but then there's some second order
um considerations about still using
language and then uh the
self-organization I thought well just
pouring water on a mountain landscape
the water is going to self-organize but
it might not
follow the path of least action to
organize the way you want
okay so then you modify the generative
model or the generative process and you
put
um a ditch here and a wall here and
again it follows a path of least action
and it self-organizes given the
constraints so it's like a combination
of whatever will be will be however it
unfolds is how it is going to unfold we
can't really dissent from that level of
tautology
however that is the space which
modifications of the niche and of the
generative model can then self-organize
to be whatever it will be
that speaks a lot too to like the
receptivity
and um action or interaction active
inference is interactive with the
environment and the niche the inability
to separate those things
uh okay so he says so bad this is back
here free energy governance provides
Rich a new meaning to existing Concepts
and establishes new relationships so
this is another one of the new
relationships um the Bijan claims he
says enactment coined by Carl Wick and
astutely applied by
smirchich and stubborn to strategy
process has conceptually inspired free
energy governance and he goes on to say
enactment is redefined as an act of
inference essentially free energy
governance is liberating upper echelon
from the overwhelming cognitive
distortion that their biggest challenge
is taming or taming uncertainty when
instead they should be really surfing it
um and like that this is kind of these
cool two references he throws in here
unless the environment is redefined as a
purpose-directed an action-centric
generative prediction challenge in the
form of prediction error minimization
firms will continue being incapacitated
by the faithful pursuit of adaptive
Fitness more importantly redefining
strategy as top-down bottom-up
predictive coding lays the foundation to
optimally leverage and co-evolve the
human machine potential
cognition
um I don't know if you guys have
comments here on this or we can move on
if not
okay
um and then the third relationship that
Bijan describes is he says Dynamic board
capabilities in the form of Duality
management are an entirely new genre of
upper echelon capabilities that FEG
establishes he goes on to say that
inactive prediction processing becomes
manifest in Duality Management in the
form of balancing financial and
strategic control as well as
exploitation and exploration Duality
management is all about probabilistic
resource reconfigurations in
superposition waiting to be enacted
Duality stewardship is feg's essential
governance mandate and then he continues
later the r d or research and
development percentage share of total
revenues is potentially a good indicator
of a looming Financial control trap
within each industry there is a rough
percentage Benchmark for r d investment
for organic reinvention once a firm
operates year on year below industry r d
investment standards Financial control
is likely to be the only control left
um and describes that as the
capabilities and so here like I I really
appreciated the section of the book
because I think that we're starting to
get some good like how do we know if
we're minimizing free energy how do we
know if we're um adapting free energy
governance like what are we doing a good
job what are the benchmarks like these
are the kinds of things that I'm looking
for and so here I liked this like you
have to be investing at least the
minimum industry industry standard into
research and development
um to ensure that like that's you're
doing the Strategic part and not just
like going for financial exploit
exploitation
um like the r d is the exploration part
and so I thought that this is kind of a
concrete application of what we've been
looking at so far Daniel
yes thank you the superposition it's a
Quantum shout out and it made me think
about some tasks that needs to be done
we need to vectorize some images and
then print stickers
there's a superposition of plans
we could upskill we could hire somebody
we could acquire the company we could do
all of these different plans including
crossovers with the different plans and
those pure plans
maybe in their extreme form are never
even on the table but
the organization can think of its
strategy as this mixed state that is
truly quantum
and it's doing a Quantum optimization
over those Pathways maybe not even
needing to Brute Force through them but
rather just letting the quantum
annealing work its magic so that's one
interesting and then the other piece is
um
like you mentioned blue once the firm
is below a critical point in its
research and development only financial
control is left and so it's almost like
um if if there's still wiggle room to
turn left and right it's still a very
maneuverable car
but if you're in a position where only
one of those sides wiggle can only
happen to One Direction like okay well
now we need to be cutting costs that's
our only degree of freedom is cutting
costs now
it doesn't even say that's not going to
be a functional strategy just that that
is on that pathway to entropic decline
because by having a reduction of
affordances
you are on the pathway to the ultimate
reduction of affordances which is the
failure to persist and as long as you
have options on the table and the
expectation of future options on the
table if not more you're in the game of
persisting
well thank you for those thoughts
um
okay
Bijan says how to make it all work in
practice is a daunting task there is no
best practices catalog first of all best
practices should be considered a
potential source of inertia like throw
those things out the window we don't
need them we need first or principles to
empower structural organization formal
and informal throughput environmental
engagement and capability to Foster
self-organizing processes free energy
governance does exactly this
um and Tyler you had spoken earlier to
like the throwing away best practices
also or like there is not a map to do
that here in free energy governance so
um
though it's also the case to be like
make this analogy between like Fairview
governance and creativity of
spirituality like it's always the case
where they can't say like okay here's
all of these steps and this is exactly
how it's going to work out for you but I
think what's effective a lot of times
too to say like hey well this is what it
doesn't look like
um like for example if you find yourself
um
kind of enslaved to your addictions for
example you may not be on like the
spiritual this spiritual path or you may
be kind of like off course a little bit
right so there are things that you can
point to say okay well
I can't say Define what it is I can't
Define what it isn't
that and I think we have some like good
Clues to that from this book even though
it might not be as prescriptive as we
might like
all right and speaking of um persisting
I wanted to I almost wanted to like skip
to the slide directly um like why should
this business exist and Prevail in the
first place like John asked this
question in the middle of the book and
like I don't know why any of us exist or
Prevail in the first place like we're
all just hanging out minimizing free
energy
um taking the path of least action I
guess uh it's just interesting like why
did why do you exist in Prevail and
um he encourages people to like ask
themselves this
um as part of like the governance
mandate um what like why should we exist
and Prevail for what for what reason
um I thought think that's always a good
question
yeah one thought on that
we can always take the
um how did things come to be
question and just whether we take that
descriptively or as a mystery but given
where we are or how we recognize
ourselves it's a little bit like a Stay
or Leave question we can stay on our
path of least action or we can push the
trim tab a little bit push the rudder a
little bit and then be on a different
path of least action so again we don't
get to dissent from being on a path at
least action but we have affordances
which are our space of local adjacencies
and this claim as I think you're
pointing to it's something that the
individual employee could ask themselves
it's something that the team could ask
themselves or the department and the the
organization and maybe the
organization's level conversation is
happening in the boardroom for certain
kinds of organizations and it's like
should we make the next six months look
a lot like the last six months
should we pivot in this direction or
should we just shut it down
and having a space for those kinds of
multi-level questions and and meaning
finding
I think part of the subtext is that's
not a waste of time that's not us uh uh
distraction from the work itself this is
like the fountain that the work
performance or alignment on any given
scale actually flows from
yeah just uh I'm not like I think the
context of this book has been like large
corporations that there's like a legal
mandate for this thing to exist and for
you to like meet the obligations of your
um your people who are financing the
business whereas like there might be
more of like lifestyle businesses you
might have or there might be a
non-profit or something where like the
free energy governance mandate to like
survive at all costs may not make as
much sense like maybe this business
organization has more of an extension of
like your personal passion uh rather
than being this own entity that needs to
survive on its own terms right so I
think it's also important to reflect
like okay like free energy governance is
this useful frame for thinking about it
but like am I really trying to create
this larger entity that exists
independently of myself or is this
um like who am I actually trying to do
here and is this a relevant framework
one other thought on that with the
organism organization conversation to
mind
are we a seasonal grass
are we a 17-year cicada
and then have that conversation even if
that's playful or in the beginning
stages of team formation or of dial
formation so that if some people think
that they're going to be building the
100 000 year
Arctic vaults and some other group of
people think that they're doing a
one-time concert
that those can be like recognized and
integrated in a way that isn't just
um as much of just like
keep things going which is how maybe
this question can seem at first pass
that it's just about existence and and
prevalence
but existence and prevalence in the
biological spaces so rich and complex
that it would make sense it would be
that way for organizations too
definitely
um okay and then here
um
quotes like and this is part of a long
quote and we're going to carry over
these over across the next two slides
but he says Jan stahlberg's practice
relevant statements from stelberg 2021
the reference if anybody wants to look
it up concerning transparency
communication and reaching out to the
bottom should Inspire management
practice
um the first of these statements is
everyone is informed in real time about
everything and then stauber goes on to
say I believe looking at some of the
core propositions of free energy
governance this is free energy
governance connecting top and bottom in
circular causality of sense making with
the least friction and optimal response
time
um so this is like something that I've
wondered about like how do you
prioritize information flow top down
bottom-up belief propagation and message
passing and like they're saying like
full transparency everybody knows
everything all of the time and um that
to me was kind of uh like mind-blowing
because it's not how I would ever think
to run a company like not at all
Daniel
okay I I hear you on that I have a
slightly different reading here
um I'm just imagining
starting with this agreement
wherever you are there you are so
whatever you're informed about that's
what you're informed about whatever your
situational awareness is that's what it
is
and then that's the part that's been
infuriating there's no suggestions for
who should be in what messaging Channel
or who should be on what email thread or
who should be in what video chat
but whatever we do decide with the chats
and the emails and the meetings that
will be your local message passing your
information environment your
capacity of for inference and action so
I don't think this means that every
single employee or contractor has the
full dashboard
I think everyone's dashboard is
respected though as their dashboard
which helps
bring the discussion to like what
function what accessibility do they need
and so on
yeah I think I think this is part one
but John was talking about a management
Theory called like open governance I
think it was called which is like the
extreme version of everyone knows
everything all the time and he was
criticizing that because he was saying
well maybe give everybody all the
information all the time that doesn't
necessarily give them the tools for
making meaning of that or having that be
relevant to like their specific context
so I think what he's implying here is
like yes like you give everyone like
everyone access the information as well
as tools for processing that information
and like a locally relevant way I don't
think he means just like pure chaos
information done I could be reading into
it
okay Blues paused but I hear you on that
Tyler
cool
I think her internet may have cut out
yes
cool
what other parts have you found
interesting so far oh there you go your
back lift
your back blue maybe you can disable
your videos
I think
you can disable your video blow
I want to give a thought on some
synchronous and asynchronous things but
you never really know when it will be
now and real for blue
but we're in a different now and real
moment Tyler
I think he's back I think she's back in
our now
okay continue blue thank you it was it
was fine it's all fine
okay
um okay so um
this is again to continue quoting
stelberg value Creation in my experience
has been usually determined by a
combination of the following governance
imperatives first you must start with a
clear purpose and long-term goal prepare
to invest for the long term and
infrastructure second you need to
continuously question yourself paranoia
is key third team decisions are critical
create a culture that empowers and
encourages people to contribute to take
decisions and not to be risk-averse in
summary it really comes down to three
things communication transparency and
respect
um and so like reading this whole quote
in context is kind of what
made me think that like they're
encouraging open channels of
communication everything flows to all
the people all the time
um but that was just it might not be
um the read the correct reading
um and and I do think that in more in
what you're saying Daniel like you have
your information Channel and like you
live in that River and like that is
where everything comes to you in real
time and whatever like you're just in
the river that you can sense me about
right like you don't necessarily need to
be in the ocean when you live in a river
um and then that makes more sense to me
in terms of of information flow
do you guys have more thoughts here on
value creation
transparency respect communication no
okay
um all right
so
ber goes on to say
the essential oh no this is actually
sorry so bhajans says the essential
governance Challenge in a discontinuous
and distributive world is now a matter
of setting free the self-organizing
optimization of top-down bottom-up
prediction error minimization learning
to infer the firm is the generative
model The Continuous nature of strategic
renewal makes prediction modeling as
well as prediction error minimization
and integral and direct default mode
Network Centric dimension of traditional
monitoring advisory and Boundary
spanning board responsibilities
effectively in the absence of
board-level medic capabilities as
developed in this book the board can no
longer fulfill even its most basic and
traditional responsibilities
um and I think that maybe Bhajan here is
calling out like
the discontinuous nature of the world
and how like disruptions are regular
um and like things move fast like change
is always happening and um you know the
Board needs to get on board or not
um but that's the wrap-up of this
chapter do you guys have any thoughts on
this
well one thing is
whatever is working in the niche today
if you expect the niche to remain the
same
you can keep your strategy the same and
it will be the same however
biological ecosystems have variability
and patterns over different time scales
and also organisms and organizations
develop so it'd be like saying
if the two-year-old baby
can't fulfill its meta capability to
learn and to change it will eventually
no longer be able to fill even its most
basic and traditional responsibilities
and so that is where we start to see
General claims about system
operation and development and evolution
and potentially the ways those are
linked in the fep
with the kinds of conversations that
today can happen
by differently framing the upper echelon
Frontline dialectic
cool I think that that's it so we're
gonna get in next week to discuss
the last two
um sections of the book and then
hopefully bring John and maybe you if
you're interested anyone else who's
interested in maybe discussing this
material hopefully we'll get some new
voices and perspectives that would
really be great
so thanks guys nice to see you
thank you bye